The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: So let's begin.
Today, I'm going to
review linear algebra.
So I'm assuming that you
already took some linear algebra
course.
And I'm going to just review
the relevant content that
will appear again and again
throughout the course.
But do interrupt me if some
concepts are not clear,
if you don't remember some
concept from linear algebra.
I hope you do.
But please let me know.
I just don't know.
You have very different
background knowledge.
So it's hard to tune
to one special group.
So I tailored this
lecture notes so that it's
a review for those who took
the most basic linear algebra
course.
So if you already
have that experience,
and don't understand it, please
feel free to interrupt me.
So I'm going to start by
talking about matrices.
A matrix, in a very
simple form, is just
a collection of numbers.
For example
[1, 2, 3; 2, 3, 4;  4, 5, 10].
You can pick any number of
rows, any number of columns.
You just write down
numbers in a square format.
And that's the matrix.
What's special about it?
So what kind of data can
you arrange in a matrix?
So I'll take an example,
which looks relevant to us.
So for example, we can index the
rows by stocks, by companies,
like Apple.
Morgan Stanley should be
there, and then Google.
And then maybe we can
index the column by dates.
I'll say July 1st, October
1st, September 1st.
And the numbers, you can
pick whatever data you want.
But probably the
sensible data will
be the stock price on that day.
I don't know for example
400, 500, and 5,000.
That would be great.
So these kind of data,
that's just the matrix.
So defining a matrix
is really simple.
But why is it so powerful?
So that's an application
point of view,
just as a collection of data.
But from a theoretical
point of view,
a matrix, an m by n
matrix, is an operator.
It defines a linear
transformation.
A defines a linear
transformation
from the vector space,
n-dimensional vector
space to the m-dimensional
vector space.
That sounds a lot more
abstract than this.
So for example, let's just
take a very small example.
If I use a 2 by 2
matrix, [2, 0;  0, 3].
Then [2, 0; 0, 3] times, let's
say [1, 1] is just [2, 3].
Does that makes sense?
It's just matrix multiplication.
So now try to combine
the point of view.
What does it mean to have a
linear transformation defined
by a data set?
And things start
to get confusing.
What is it?
Why does a data set define
a linear transformation?
And does it have any
sensible meaning?
So that's a good question
to have in mind today.
And try to remember
this question.
Because today I'll
try to really develop
a theory of eigenvalues and
eigenvectors in a purely
theoretical language.
But it can still be
applied to these data sets,
and give very
important properties
and very important quantities.
You can get some useful
information out of it.
Try to make sense out
of why it happens.
So that will be the goal today,
to really treat linear algebra
as a theoretical thing.
But remember that there's some
data set, like really data set
underlying.
This doesn't go up.
That was a bad choice
for my first board.
Sorry.
So the most important concepts
for us are the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors
of a matrix, which
is defined as a real number,
lambda, and vector v,
is an eigenvalue, and
eigenvector of a matrix A,
if A times v is equal to
lambda times V. We also
say that v is an eigenvector
corresponding to lambda.
So remember eigenvalues
and eigenvectors always
come in pairs.
And they are defined by the
property that A*v = lambda*v.
First question, does all
matrix have eigenvalues
and eigenvectors?
Nope?
So Av-- It looks like this
is a very strange equation
to satisfy.
But if you change it in this
form, (A - lambda I)v = 0.
That still looks strange.
But at least you
understand that-- it's
an only if, this can happen
only if this can happen.
Happens only if A - lambda
I does not have full rank.
So determinant of (A - lambda I)
is equal to 0, if and only if,
in fact.
So now comes a very
interesting observation.
det(A - lambda I) is a
polynomial of degree n.
I made a mistake.
I should have said, this is
only for n by n matrices.
This is only for
square matrices.
Sorry.
It's a polynomial of degree n.
That means it has a solution.
It has to give n
in terms of lambda.
So it has a solution.
It might be a complex number.
I'm really sorry.
I'm nervous in
front of the video.
I understand why you were saying
that is doesn't necessarily
exist.
Let me repeat.
I made a few mistakes here.
So let me repeat here.
For n by n matrix A, a complex
number lambda, and the vector
v, is an eigenvalue
and eigenvector
if it satisfies this condition.
It doesn't have to be real.
Sorry about that.
And now if we
rephrase it this way,
because this is a
polynomial, it always
has at least one solution.
That was just a side point.
Very theoretical.
So we see that there
always exists at least one
eigenvalue and eigenvector.
Now we saw its existence, what
is the geometrical meaning
of it?
Now let's go back to the linear
transformation point of view.
So suppose A is a 3 by 3 matrix.
Then A takes the vector in R^3
and transforms it into another
vector in R^3.
But if you have this
relation, what's
going to happen is
A, when applied to v,
it will just scale the vector
v. If this was the original v,
A of v will just be
lambda times this vector.
That will be our Av, which
is equal to lambda v.
So eigenvectors are
those special vectors
which when applied this
linear transformation just
get scaled by some amount, where
that amount is exactly lambda.
So what we established so
far, what we recall so far
is every n by n matrix has
at least one such direction.
There is some vector where the
linear transformation defined
by A just scales that vector.
Which is quite
interesting, if you ever
thought about it before.
There's no reason such
vector should exist.
Of course I'm
lying a little bit.
Because these might
be complex vectors.
But at least in the
complex world it's true.
So if you think about
this, this is very helpful.
It gives you the vectors-- from
these vectors' point of view,
this linear transformation
is really easy to understand.
That's why eigenvalues and
eigenvector are so good.
It breaks down the
linear transformation
into really simple operations.
Let me formalize that
a little bit more.
So in an extreme case a
matrix, an n by n matrix A,
we call it
diagonalizable, if there
exists an orthonormal
matrix, I'll
call what it is, U, such that
A is equal to U times D times U
inverse for a diagonal matrix D.
Let me iterate through
this a little bit.
What is an orthonormal matrix?
It's a matrix defined by the
relation U times U transposed
is equal to the identity.
What is a diagonal matrix?
It's a matrix whose
nonzero entries are all
on the diagonal.
All the rest are zero.
Why is it so good to
have this decomposition?
What does it mean to have an
orthonormal matrix like this?
It means basically I'll just
explain what's happening.
If that happens, if a
matrix is diagonalizable,
if this A is
diagonalizable, there
will be three directions,
v_1, v_2, v_3,
such that when you apply this
A, v_1 scales by some lambda_1.
v_2 scales by some lambda_2.
And v_3 scales by some lambda_3.
So we can completely understand
the transformation A,
just in terms of
these three vectors.
So this, the stuff here will
be the most important things
you'll use in linear algebra
throughout this course.
So let me repeat
it really slowly.
So an eigenvalue and eigenvector
is defined by this relation.
We know that there are at least
one eigenvalue for each matrix,
and there is an eigenvector
corresponding to it.
And eigenvectors have
this geometrical meaning
where-- a vector
is an eigenvector,
if the linear
transformation defined
by A just scales that vector.
So for our setting,
the real good matrices
are the matrices which
can be broken down
into these directions.
And those directions
are defined by this U.
And D defines how
much it will scale.
So in this case U will
be our v_1, v_2, v_3.
And D will be our lambda_1,
lambda_2, lambda_3 all 0.
Any questions so far?
So that is abstract.
Now remember the question
I posed in the beginning.
So remember that matrix where we
had stocks and dates and stock
prices in the entries?
What will an eigenvector
of that matrix mean?
What will an eigenvalue mean?
So try to think
about that question.
It's not like it will have
some physical counterpart.
But there's some really
interesting things
going on there.
The bad news is that not all
matrices are diagonalizable.
If a matrix is diagonalizable,
it's really easy
to understand what it does.
Because it really breaks down
into these three directions,
if it's a 3 by 3.
If it's an n by n, it breaks
down into n directions.
Unfortunately, not all
matrices are diagonalizable.
But there is a
very special class
of matrices which are
always diagonalizable.
And fortunately we
will see those matrices
throughout the course.
Most of the matrices,
n by n matrices,
we will study, fall
into this category.
So an n by n matrix
A is symmetric
if A is equal to A transpose.
Before proceeding,
please raise your hand
if you're familiar with
all the concepts so far.
OK.
Good feeling.
So a matrix is symmetric if
it's equal to its transpose.
A transpose is obtained
by taking the mirror
image across the diagonal.
And then it is known that
all symmetric matrices
are diagonalizable.
Ah, I've made another mistake.
Orthonormally.
So with this I missed matrices
orthonormally diagonalizable.
So it's diagonalizable if
we drop this condition,
and replace it
with an invertible.
So symmetric matrices
are really good.
And fortunately most of the n
by n matrices that we will study
are symmetric.
Just by the nature of
it, it will be symmetric.
The one I gave as an
example is not symmetric.
It's not symmetric.
But I will address
that issue in a minute.
And another important
thing is symmetric matrices
have real eigenvalues.
So really this geometrical
picture just the--
for symmetric
matrices, this picture
is really the picture
you should have in mind.
So proof of Theorem 2.
Suppose lambda is an eigenvalue
with eigenvector v. Then
by definition we have this.
Now multiply v
transposed on both sides.
It is lambda times the norm v.
Now take the complex
conjugate-- Real symmetric.
And then first A conjugate,
we have v^T A^T v,
and then take the
conjugate of it.
Then we get lambda...
v. And this side is
equal to v^T A^T v.
But because A is real symmetric,
we see that A is equal
to the conjugate of
complex conjugate of A.
So this expression and this
expression is the same.
The right side should
also be the same.
That means lambda is equal
to the conjugate of lambda.
So lambda has to be a real.
So Theorem 1 is a little
bit more complicated,
and it involves more
advanced concepts
like basis and linear
subspace, and so on.
And those concepts
are not really
important for this class.
So I'll just skip the proof.
But it's really important to
remember these two theorems.
Wherever you see
a symmetric matrix
you should really feel like
you have control on it.
Because you can diagonalize it.
And moreover, all
eigenvalues are real,
and you have really good
control on symmetric matrices.
That's good.
That was when
everything went well.
We can diagonalize it.
So, so far we saw that if
for a symmetric matrix,
we can diagonalize it.
It's really easy to understand.
But what about general matrices?
In general, not all matrices are
diagonalizable, first of all.
But sometimes we still want
to decomposition like this.
So diagonalization was A equals
U times D times U inverse.
But we want something similar.
We want to understand.
So our goal, we want to
still understand the matrix,
give a matrix A through simple
operations, such as scaling.
When the matrix was a
diagonalizable matrix this
was done, this was possible.
Unfortunately, it's not
always diagonalizable.
So we have to do something else.
So that's what I
want to talk about.
And luckily the
good news is there
is a nice tool we can
use for all matrices,
even those slightly weaker,
in fact, a little bit more
weaker than this
diagonalization.
But still it distills some
very important information
of the matrix.
So it's called singular
value decomposition.
So this will be our second
tool of understanding matrices.
It's very similar to
this diagonalization,
or in other words I call this
eigenvalue decomposition.
But it has a slightly
different form.
So what is its form?
So theorem.
Let A be an m by n matrix.
Then there always exists
orthonormal matrices
U and V such that A is
equal to U times sigma times
V transpose.
For some diagonal matrix sigma.
Let me parse through the
theorem a little bit more.
Whenever you're
given a matrix, it
doesn't even have to be
a square matrix anymore.
It can be non-symmetric.
So whenever we're given an
m by n matrix, in general,
there always exists
two matrices, U and V,
which are orthonormal,
such that A
can be decomposed as U times
sigma times V transposed, where
sigma is a diagonal matrix.
But now the size of the
matrix are important
so U is an m by n matrix,
sigma is an m by n matrix,
and V is an n by n matrix.
That just denotes the size,
the dimensions of the matrix.
So what does it mean for an
m by n matrix to be diagonal?
It just means the same thing.
So only the (i,i) entries
are allowed to be nonzero.
So that was just
a bunch of words.
So let me rephrase this.
So let me compare now eigenvalue
decomposition, with singular
value decomposition.
So this is EVD, what
we just saw before.
It only-- SVD.
This only works for
n by n matrices,
which are diagonalizable.
SVD works for all
general m by n matrices.
However, this is powerful.
Because it gives you one frame.
So v_1 with a v_2, v_3 for which
A acts as a scaling operator.
Kind of like that.
That's what A does,
A does, A does.
That's because these U on
the both sides are equal.
However, for singular
value decomposition,
this is called singular
value decomposition.
I just erased It.
What you have instead
is first of all,
the spaces are different.
If you take a vector in
R^m, and bring it to R^n,
apply this operation A. What's
going to happen here is there
will be one frame in here,
and one frame in here.
So there will be vectors
v_1, v_2, v_3, v_4 like this.
And there will be vectors
u_1, u_2, u_3 like this here.
And what's going to happen
is when you take v_1,
A will take v_1 to u_1
and scale it a little bit
according to that diagonal.
A will take v_2 to
u_2, it will scale it.
It'll take v_3 to u_3, scale it.
Wait a minute.
But for v_4, we don't have u_4.
What's going to happen is this
is just going to disappear.
u_4, when applied
A, will disappear.
So I know it's a very
vague explanation,
but this geometric picture,
try to compare them.
A diagonalization,
eigenvalue decomposition,
works within its frame, so
it's very, very powerful.
You just have some directions
and you scale those directions.
But the singular
value composition
it's applicable to a more
general class of matrices,
but it's rather more restricted.
You have two frames, one
for the original space, one
for the target space.
And what the linear
transformation does is,
it just sends one
vector to another vector
and scales it a little bit.
So now is another
good time to go back
to that matrix in
the very beginning.
So remember that example where
we had a vector of companies,
and dates, and the
entry was stock prices.
So if it's an n by
n matrix, you can
try to apply both
eigenvalue decomposition,
and singular value
decomposition.
But what will be more sensible
is singular value decomposition
in this case.
I won't explain why, and
what's happening here.
Peter will probably.
You will come to it later.
But just try to do some
imagining before listening
what's really happening
in real world.
So try to use your own
imagination, your own language
to express.
See what happens for
this matrix, what
this decomposition is doing.
It just looks like
totally nonsense.
Why does this have
even a geometry?
Why does it define a linear
transformation and so on?
It's just a beautiful
theory, which just
gives many useful information.
I can't really emphasize more.
Because-- emphasize
enough, because really
this is just universal, being
used in all science, these.
I think the eigenvalue
decomposition, and the singular
value decomposition.
Not just for this
course, but pretty much
it's safe to say in
every engineering,
you'll encounter
one of the forms.
So let me talk about the
proof of the singular value
decomposition.
And I will show you an
example of what singular value
decomposition does for some
example matrix, the matrix
that I chose.
Proof of singular
value decomposition,
which is interesting.
It relies on eigenvalue
decomposition.
So given a matrix A, consider
the eigenvalues of A times
A transpose.
Oh, A transpose A. First
observation: that's
a symmetric matrix.
So if you remember, it
will have real eigenvalues,
and it's diagonalizable.
So A^T of A has eigenvalues
lambda_1, lambda_2,
up to, it's an n by n
matrix, so lambda_n.
And corresponding eigenvectors
v_1, v_2, up to v_n.
And so for convenience, I
will cut it at lambda_r,
and assume all rest is 0.
So there might be
none which are 0.
In that case we use
all the eigenvalues.
But I only am interested
in nonzero eigenvalues.
So I'll say up to
lambda_r, they're nonzero.
Afterwards it's 0.
It's just a notational choice.
And now I'm just
going to make a claim
that they're all positive.
This part is kind
of just believe me.
Then if that's the case, we
can rewrite the eigenvalues.
Rewrite eigenvalues as
sigma_1^2, sigma_2^2,
sigma_r^2, and 0.
That was my first step.
My second step,
that was step one,
step two is to define
u_1 as A*v_1 / sigma_1,
u_2 as A*v_2 / sigma_2.
And u_r as A*V_r / sigma_r.
And then u times r+1
as-- up to u times m,
as complete the
above into a basis.
So for those who
don't understand,
just think of we pick u_1
up to u_r first, and then
arbitrarily pick the rest.
And you'll see why I only care
about the nonzero eigenvalues.
Because I have to divide by
sigmas, the sigma values.
And if it's zero, I
can't do the division.
So that's why I identified
those which are not zero.
And then we're done.
So it doesn't look at
all like we're done.
But I'm going to let my U be
this, u_1, u_2, up to u_n.
Sorry, it has to be n.
My V I will pick as
v_1, v_2, up to v_r.
And then v_(r+1) up to v_n.
So this again just
complete into a basis.
Now let's see what happens.
So A times U transpose
times V. Oh, ah.
That's why it's a problem.
You have to do U times
A times V transpose.
So I would write V
is n, and this is m.
Ah yes, so U times A
times V transpose here.
That will be u_1, u_2, u_m.
A. V transpose will be v_1
transpose, v_2 transpose,
to v_n transpose.
I messed up something.
Sorry.
Oh, that's the
form I want, right?
Yeah.
So I have to transpose
U and V there.
OK, sorry.
Thank you.
Thank you for the correction.
I know this looks
different from that.
But I mean if you flip the
definition it will be the same.
So I'll just not--
stop making mistakes.
Do you have a question?
So, yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah.
That will make more sense.
Thank you very much.
And then you're going
to have u_1 transpose up
to u_n transpose.
A times V, because of
the definition of V,
will be lambda_1 of v_1.
A times v_2 will
be lambda_2 of v_2.
Up to lambda_r of v_r,
and the rest will be zero.
These all define the columns.
Now let's do a few computations.
So u_1^T times lambda_1 v_1.
u_1^T, and lambda_1 v_1.
When you take the dot product,
what you're going to get is
v_1^T A transpose
of v_1 lambda_1.
I'm missing something.
Ah, sorry about that.
This is not right.
These are As.
I defined the eigenvalues
for A transpose A.
Then that's u_1 transpose
times sigma_1 times u_1.
That will be sigma_1.
And then if you look at the
second entry, u_1 transpose
times A v_2, you get u_1
transpose times sigma_2 of u_2.
But I claim that
this is equal to 0.
So why is that the case?
u_1 transpose is
equal to V_1 transpose
A transpose over sigma_1.
And we have sigma_2.
u_2 is equal to A
times v_2 over sigma_2.
So those two cancel.
And we have v_1^T A^T
A v_2 over sigma_1.
But v_1 and v_2 are two
different eigenvectors
of this matrix.
At the beginning we can have an
orthonormal decomposition of A
transpose A. That means v_1^T
times v_2 times that has to be
equal to zero.
Because that's an eigenvalue.
We have v_1^T times
lambda_2 v_2 over sigma_1.
So we have lambda_2 over
sigma_1 times v_1 transpose v_2.
These two are
orthogonal so give 0.
So if you do the
computation, what
you're going to have
is sigma_1, sigma_2
on the diagonal, up to
sigma_r, and then 0, 0 rest.
And 0 the rest.
Sorry for the confusion.
Actually the process
is quite simple.
I was just lost in the
computation in the middle.
So process is first
look at A transpose A.
Find the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors.
And using those, they
define the matrix V.
And you can define the
matrix U by applying A times
V over sigma.
Each of those will
define the entries of U.
The reason I wanted to
go through this proof
is because this gives you a
process of finding a singular
value decomposition.
It was a little
bit painful for me.
But if you have a matrix
there's just these simple steps
you can follow to find the
singular value decomposition.
So look at this matrix, find its
eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
Just arrange it
in the right way.
Of course, the right
way needs some practice
to be done correctly.
But once you do that, you
just obtain a singular value
composition.
And really I can't explain
how powerful it is.
You will only later
see it in the course
how powerful this
decomposition will be.
And only then you'll
more appreciate
how good it is to have
this decomposition,
and be able to
compute it so simply.
So let's try to do it by hand.
Yes?
STUDENT: So when you
compute the [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Yes.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: It would have
to be orthonormal, yeah.
It should be orthonormal.
These should be orthonormal.
These also.
And that's a good point,
because that can be annoying
when you want to do it by hand.
Actually this decomposition.
You have to do some Gram-Schmidt
process or something like that.
What I mean by
hand, I don't really
mean by hand, other than
when you're doing homework.
Because you can use
the computer to do it.
And in fact, if you
use computer there
are much better algorithms
than this that are known,
which can do this a lot more
quickly and more efficiently.
So let's try to do it by hand.
So let A be this matrix:
[3, 2  2; 2, 3, -2].
And we want to make the
eigenvalue decomposition
of this.
A transpose A, we
have to compute that,
is [3, 2, 2; 2, 3, -2].
And you will get [13, 12, 2; 12,
13, -2; 2, -2, 8].
And let me just say that the
eigenvalues are 0, 9, and 25.
So in this algorithm,
sigma_1^2 will be 25.
Sigma_2^2 squared will be 9.
And sigma_3^2 squared will be 0.
So we can take sigma_1
to be 5, sigma_2 to be 3,
sigma_3 to be 0.
Now we have to find the
corresponding eigenvectors
to find the singular
value decomposition.
And I'll just do one
just to remind you
how to find an eigenvector.
So A transpose A,
minus 25I is equal to,
if you subtract 25
from these entries,
you're going to get [-12, 12, 2;
12, -12, -2; 2, -2, -13].
And then you have to
find the vector which
annihilates this matrix.
And that will be, I can take one
of those vectors to be just 1
over square root of 2, 1
over square root of two, 0,
after normalizing.
And then just do it
for other vectors.
You find v_2 to be 1 over
square root 18, negative 1
over square root 18,
4 over square root 18.
Now then find v_3 to be the
one that annihilates this.
But I'll just say it's x, y, z.
This will not be important.
I'll explain why it's
not that important.
Then our v as written
above, actually
there it was transposed.
So I will transpose it.
That will be 1 over
square root of 2,
1 over square root of 2, 0.
v_2 is that.
So we can write 1 over
square root 18, negative 1
over square root 18,
4 over square root 18.
And here just write x, y, z.
And U will be defined
as u_1 and u_2,
where u_1 is A times
v_1 over sigma_1.
u_2 is A times v_2 over sigma_2.
So multiply A by this
vector, divide by sigma_1
to get U. I already did
the computation for you.
It's going to be-- and
this is going to be-- yes?
STUDENT: How did you get v_1?
PROFESSOR: v_1?
So if you did the computation
right in the beginning to get
the eigenvalues, then A^T
A - 25I, this has to be--
has to not have full rank.
So there has to be a vector v,
which when multiplied by this
gives [0, 0, 0] vector.
And then you say [a, b, c]
and set it equal to [0, 0, 0].
And just solve the system
of linear equations.
There will be several of them.
For example, we can
take [1, 1,  0] as well.
But I just normalized
it to have [INAUDIBLE].
So there's a lot
of work involved
if you want to do it by hand,
even though you can do it.
You have to find eigenvalues,
find eigenvectors.
In this case, you have
to find three of them.
And then you have to do
more work, and more work.
But it can be done.
And we are done now.
So now this decomposes A into
U sigma V transformation.
So U is given as [1 over square
root 2, 1 over square root 2;
1 over square root 2, minus
1 over square root 2].
Sigma was 5, 3, 0.
And V is this.
So V transpose is just
transpose of that.
I'll just write it like
that, where V is that.
So we have this decomposition.
And so let me actually write
it, because I want to show you
why x, y, z is not important.
1 over square root 2,
0; 1 over square root 18,
minus 1 over square root 18,
4 over square root 18; x, y, z.
The reason I'm
saying this is not
important is because I can just
drop-- oh what did I do here?
It has to be 2 by 3.
I can just drop this column,
and drop this column together.
It has to be that form.
Drop this and drop
this altogether.
So the message here is that
the eigenvectors corresponding
to eigenvalue zero
are not important.
The only relevant ones
are nonzero eigenvalues.
So drop this, and drop this.
That will save you
some computation.
So let me state a different
form of singular value
decomposition.
So this works in general.
There's a corollary.
We get a simplified form of SVD.
Where A becomes equal to U
times sigma times V transpose.
And A was an m by n matrix.
U is still an m by m matrix.
But now sigma is
also m by m matrix.
This only works when m is
less than or equal to n.
And V is a m by n matrix.
So the proof is
exactly the same.
And the last step is just
to drop the irrelevant
information.
So I will not write
down why it works.
But you can see if
you go through it,
you'll see that
dropping this part
just corresponds to
exactly that information.
So that's the reduced form.
So let's see.
In the beginning
we had A. I erased
A. A was the 2 by 3
matrix in the beginning.
And we obtained the
decomposition into 2
by 2, 2 by 2, and 2 by 3 matrix.
If we didn't delete the
fifth column and fifth row,
we would have obtained a 2
by 2, times 2 by 3, times 3
by 3 matrix.
But now we can simplify
it by removing those.
And it might not look that
much different on this board.
Because I just erased one row.
But many matrices that you'll
see in real application
have a lot lower rank than the
number of columns and rows.
So if r is a lot more smaller
than both m and n, then
this part really--
it's not obvious here.
But if m and n has
a big gap here,
really the number of
columns that you're saving,
it can be enormous.
So to illustrate an
example, look at this.
Now look at the
stock prices, where
you have companies and dates.
Previously I just gave an
example of a 3 by 3 matrix.
But it's more sensible
to have dates, a lot
more dates than companies.
So let's say you recorded
365 days of a year,
even though the market is
not open all days, and just
like five companies.
If you did a decomposition this
this, you'll have a 5 by 5,
5 by 365, 365 by 365 here.
But now in the reduced form,
you're saving a lot of space.
So if you just
look at the board,
it doesn't look like
it's so powerful.
But in fact it is.
So that's the reduced form.
And that will be the
form that you'll see most
of the time, this reduced form.
So I made lot of mistakes today.
I have one more topic, but
a totally irrelevant topic.
So any questions before I
move on to the next topic?
Yes?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Can you
press the button?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Oh, so in
this data, what it means.
You're asking what the
eigenvectors will mean over
this data?
It will give you some stocks.
It will give you
like the correlation.
So each eigenvector
will give you
a group of companies that
are correlated somehow.
It measures their
correlation with each other.
So I don't have a
very good explanation
what its physical meaning is.
Maybe you can give
just a little bit more.
GUEST SPEAKER: Possibly.
We will get into this
in later lectures.
But in the singular
value decomposition,
what you want to think of is
these orthonormal matrices
are really defining a new basis,
sort of an orthogonal basis.
So you're taking the
original coordinate system,
then you're rotating it.
And without changing
or stretching
or squeezing the data.
You're just rotating the axes.
So an orthonormal
matrix gives you
the cosines of the
new coordinate system
with respect to the old one.
And so the singular
value decomposition
then is simply sort
of rotating the data
into a different orientation.
And the orthonormal basis
that you're transforming to,
is essentially the coordinates
of the original data
in the transformed system.
So as Choongbum was
commenting, you're essentially
looking at a representation
of the original data
points in a linearly
transformed space,
and the correlations
between different stocks,
say, is represented by how those
points are oriented in the new,
in the transformed space.
PROFESSOR: So you'll have to see
real data to really make sense
out of it.
But another way to think of
it is where it comes from.
So all this singular
value decomposition,
if you remember
the proof, it comes
from eigenvectors and
eigenvalues of A transpose A.
Now if you look at A
transpose A, or I'll just say
it's A times A transposed.
It's pretty much the same.
If you look at A
times A transpose,
you're going to get
an m by n matrix.
And it'll be indexed
both by these companies.
And the numbers
here will represent
how much the
companies are related
to each other, how
much correlation they
have between each other.
So by looking at the
eigenvectors of this matrix,
you're looking at the
correlation between these stock
prices, let's say, these
company stock prices.
And that information is
represented inside the singular
value decomposition.
But again, it's a lot
better to understand
if you have real
numbers and real data,
which you will have later.
So please be excited and wait.
You're going to see
some cool stuff.
So that was all for eigenvalue
decomposition and singular
value decomposition.
And the last thing I
want to mention today
is something called
Perron-Frobenius theorem.
This one even looks a lot
more theoretical than the ones
I showed you.
But surprisingly a few
years ago, Steve Ross,
he's a faculty in the
business school here,
found a very interesting result
called Steve Ross recovery
theorem that makes
use of this theorem,
makes use of
Perron-Frobenius theorem
that I will tell you today.
Unfortunately you will
only see a lecture
on Steve Ross recovery
theorem towards the end
of the semester.
So I will try to recall
what it is later.
But since we're talking
about linear algebra today,
let me introduce the theorem.
This is called Perron-Frobenius.
And you really won't believe
that it has any applications
in finance because it
just looks so theoretical.
I'm just stating a
really weak form.
Weak form.
Let A be an n by n symmetric
matrix, whose entries are all
positive, with positive entries.
Then there are a few
properties that they have.
First there exists
an eigenvalue,
there exists a largest
eigenvalue, lambda_0, such
that lambda is
less than lambda_0.
Well that's true for
all other lambda.
So this statement is really
easy for symmetric matrix.
So forget about-- you
can drop symmetric,
but I'm just stated it,
because I'm going to prove only
for this weak case.
Just think about the statement
when it's not symmetric.
So if you have an n by n matrix
whose entries are all positive,
then there exists an eigenvalue,
lambda_0, a real eigenvalue
such that the absolute value
of all of other eigenvalues
are strictly smaller
than this eigenvalue.
So remember that if it's
not a symmetric matrix,
they can be complex values.
This is saying that there's
a unique eigenvalue which
has largest absolute value, and
moreover, it's a real number.
Second part, there
exists an eigenvector,
a positive eigenvector
with positive entries,
corresponding to lambda 0.
So the eigenvector
corresponding to this lambda 0
has positive entries.
And the third part
is lambda_0 is
an eigenvalue of multiplicity 1,
for those who know what it is.
So this really is
a unique eigenvalue
with a unique eigenvector,
which has positive entries.
And it's larger, really
larger than other eigenvalues.
So from the mathematician
point of view,
this has many applications.
It's probability theory.
My main research area
is combinatorics,
discrete mathematics.
It's also used in there.
So from the theoretical
point of view,
this has been used
in many contexts.
It's not a standard theorem
taught in linear algebra.
So I don't think probably most
of you haven't seen it before.
But it's a well known
result, with many uses,
theoretical uses.
But you also see one use
in, later, as I mentioned,
in finance, which
is quite surprising.
So let me just give you some
feeling of why it happens.
I won't give you the full
detail of the proof, but just
a very brief description.
Sketch when A is symmetric, just
a simple case, A is symmetric.
In this case, this
statement, if you look at it.
First of all A has
real eigenvalues.
I'll say it's lambda_1,
lambda_2, up to lambda_n.
And at some point, I'll
say up to lambda_i,
it's greater than
zero, pass to where
this is smaller than zero.
There are some
positive eigenvalues.
negative eigenvalues.
So that's observation one.
Things are more easy to control,
because they are all real.
The first statement says that--
maybe I should have indexed it
as lambda_0.
I'll just call this
lambda 0 instead.
This lambda_0 is in fact
larger in absolute value
than lambda_n.
That's the content
of the first bullet.
So if they all have all
positive entries, then
the positive, largest
positive eigenvalue
dominates the smallest negative
eigenvalue, which yeah.
So why is that the case?
First of all, to
see that you have
to go through different steps.
So we go into observation two.
Lambda_1, so look at lambda_1.
lambda_1 has an eigenvector
with positive entries.
Why is that the case?
That's because if
you look at A times v
equals lambda times v. If
v-- let me state it this way.
Lambda_0 is the maximum
of all lambda, lambda_0.
That's not entirely correct.
Lambda_1.
Sorry about that.
So If you look at this, if
v has non-positive entries,
if it has a negative entry,
if v has a negative entry,
then flip it.
Flip the sign, and in this
way obtain new vector v prime.
Since A has positive entries,
A has positive entries.
What we conclude
is that A times v
prime will be larger than A
times v. You have to look.
Think about, because it
has positive entries,
if it had some negative
part somewhere,
the magnitude will decrease.
So if you flip the sign it
should increase the magnitude.
And this cannot happen.
This shouldn't happen.
This should not happen.
That's where the positive
entries part is used.
If you have positive
entries, then it should have,
the eigenvector should have
positive entries as well.
So I will not work through
the details of the rest.
I will post it on
the lecture notes.
But really this
theorem, in fact,
can be stated in a lot
more generality than this.
I'm stating only
a very weak form.
It doesn't have to have
all positive entries.
It has to only be something
called irreducible,
which is a concept from
probability theory,
from Markov chains.
But here we will only
use it in this setting.
So I will review it later,
before it's really being used.
But just remember that how
these positive entries kick
into this kind of
statement, where
there is an eigenvalue,
largest eigenvalue, why
there has to be a vector
which is all positive entries.
Those will all come
into play later.
So I think that's it for today.
If you have any last
minute questions?
If not, I will see
you on Thursday.